<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0">
    <channel>
      <title>SeniorMars - essay</title>
      <link>https://seniormars.com</link>
      <description>A blog about math, extremely niche interests, and a guy having fun.</description>
      <generator>Zola</generator>
      <language>en</language>
      <atom:link href="https://seniormars.com/tags/essay/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
      <lastBuildDate>Wed, 06 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
      <item>
          <title>A Critique Of The Mathematical Proof: What Happens Now?</title>
          <pubDate>Wed, 06 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
          <author>SeniorMars</author>
          <link>https://seniormars.com/posts/proof/</link>
          <guid>https://seniormars.com/posts/proof/</guid>
          <description xml:base="https://seniormars.com/posts/proof/">&lt;h1 id=&quot;motivation&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#motivation&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: motivation&quot;&gt;Motivation&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I get deeper into my undergrad for mathematics, I realized that I came to
love Logic; for the longest time, I believe that mathematics was an extension
of this love. Yet, the more I read, the more I learned about the fallacies of
mathematics. This piece is a critique of the mathematical proof, a reflection
on my own thoughts, and a way to introduce my concerns to the world as an
introduction piece. I hope you enjoy it: especially the &lt;a href=&#x27;#poem&#x27;&gt;poem&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; at the end.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Proofs are at the heart of mathematics — a discipline that concerns itself with
the precise and rigorous development of ideas to find the “truth.”
Unfortunately, while math strives for correctness through deduction, how we
construct proofs contradicts the idea that math tries to be. Succinctly, the
fallacy of proofs is illustrated through the difference in how proofs are
constructed in theory and practice. In theory, proofs are a series of logical
statements that follow from other logical claims — a definition posed by
Aristotle centuries ago — that seek to convince a reader of a claim or a truth
&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-1-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-1&quot;&gt;1&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;. In practice, however, proofs are written in natural language, often
imprecise and ambiguous. The discrepancy between theory and practice is a
fundamental problem in mathematics, especially when proofs are how
mathematicians establish the validity of their claims and communicate their
results to others. Nevertheless, it has become clear to me that this problem
has been apparent to many throughout the history of mathematics. Several
individuals have tried to reason about logic and this problem through
mathematical systems — fighting mathematics with mathematics. But the question
remains: what happens now? How do we address the fallacy of proofs in
mathematics?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;introduction-towards-formal-verification&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#introduction-towards-formal-verification&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: introduction-towards-formal-verification&quot;&gt;Introduction towards Formal Verification&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In principle, the academic world has prevented this fallacy through peer
review, a process that many have criticized &lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-2-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-2&quot;&gt;2&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt; due to its various
shortcomings. While peer review “adds a bit of certainty” &lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-3-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-3&quot;&gt;3&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt; to mathematical
work, it is not an end–all solution to the problem of human error. A prominent
example of this flaw can be highlighted through a dynamical system theorem
published in 1970 by Noel Baker. Once published, the theorem was subsequently
used to prove various results in dynamical systems; in turn, these results were
generalized and furthered–establishing the influence of Baker’s theorem in the
field. However, half a century later, a pair of mathematicians discovered a
flaw in Baker’s proof, a flaw so grave that it invalidated the
theorem — returning its status as an open problem &lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-4-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-4&quot;&gt;4&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;. This example
illustrates the potential for human error in mathematical proofs and the
consequences of such errors. Moreover, since the 20th century, this issue has
been exacerbated by the increasing complexity of mathematical proofs.
Mathematics is now at a stage where it has become so complex that the field
is beyond the comprehension of a single mathematician; a new proof is built
upon the work of many mathematicians, each trusting the work of the other. A
new approach to the mathematical proof is needed; fortunately, a growing field
seeks to address these problems at once: Formal Verification.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Formal Verification emerges as a promising solution to the fallacy of
mathematical proofs. It is a framework that extends the original purpose of
proofs, focusing on verifying the correctness of a system or model through the
use of mathematical techniques. For our purposes, formal Verification treats
proofs as mathematical objects and checks their correctness through a program,
offering a metamathematical approach to mathematics. To fully grasp the
implications of Formal Verification, we delve into its historical development,
the often misunderstood relationship between computer science and mathematics,
and the pivotal role of Type Theory in Formal Verification. We then introduce
the Lean Theorem Prover, a programming language that verifies the correctness
of mathematical proofs. Finally, we talk about the Lean programming language to
the context of Partial Differential Equations, providing insights into the
future of mathematics.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;preliminaries&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#preliminaries&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: preliminaries&quot;&gt;Preliminaries&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The notion of studying proofs as mathematical objects was popularized through
the concept of “Gödel Numbering” in the early 1930s. The technique provided a
method to transform an object in any formal language, i.e., proofs in formal
logic, to a unique natural number through a bijective function &lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-5-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-5&quot;&gt;5&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;. While the
idea of formal methods can be attributed to Gottfried Wilhelm Leibniz — as
Leibniz wished for a universal, correct, and logical language &lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-6-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-6&quot;&gt;6&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt; — Gödel’s
incompleteness theorems were the true beginning of the field. These theorems
explored the limitations of formal systems with notions of “numbers”; as many
branches of mathematics relied on ZFC-Set Theory, Gödel’s impact was profound.
In short (and imprecisely), Gödel’s theorems showed that any formal system
powerful enough to express arithmetic was either inconsistent or incomplete.
These results could be interpreted as the first major hurdle to mathematical
formalization, a problem that has yet to be fully resolved. In fact, David
Hilbert, a prominent figure in many fields, sought to formalize all mathematics
through his project, the Foundations of Mathematics, which failed as Gödel’s
work showed that Hilbert’s approach was doomed to fail. Gödel’s work was so
influential that it led to the creation of the field of Proof Theory, the study
of proofs&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-7-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-7&quot;&gt;7&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;. Ultimately, the first major hurdle to mathematics only
emphasized the need for a new approach to proofs.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;where-computer-science-and-mathematics-meet&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#where-computer-science-and-mathematics-meet&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: where-computer-science-and-mathematics-meet&quot;&gt;Where Computer Science and Mathematics Meet&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For the longest time, a common misconception persists that formal verification
has only been a staple in computer science — that its application to pure
mathematics is a recent development. Although, the reason for this
misconception is largely unknown to philosophers — this view, however,
overlooks the intricate relationship between computer science and mathematics,
as well as the historical trajectory of formal verification itself.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Formal verification emerged as a distinct field within computer science in the
1970s, with the primary objective of verifying software correctness &lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-8-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-8&quot;&gt;8&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;. This
pursuit was driven by the recognition that software bugs could lead to
catastrophic consequences. A stark illustration of this potential for disaster
is the Therac-25 incident, where a radiation therapy machine malfunctioned due
to software errors, resulting in severe radiation overdoses to patients &lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-9-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-9&quot;&gt;9&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;.
Such incidents underscored the critical need for rigorous verification methods
in software development. The importance of formal verification in computer
science is further exemplified by NASA’s stringent requirements. The space
agency mandates that compilers used in mission-critical software development be
formally verified, although this requirement does not extend to the executable
code itself as it should be &lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-10-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-10&quot;&gt;10&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;. This practice highlights the recognition of
formal verification as a crucial tool for ensuring the reliability and safety
of complex systems. Clearly, the techniques of Formal Verification have been a
cornerstone of computer science for decades. However, to fully grasp the
significance of its application to mathematics, we must explore the
intricate relationship between programs and proofs — addressing the
misconception that the two are distinct entities. We begin by introducing the
basics of Constructive Mathematics, Type Theory, and the Curry-Howard
correspondence, which form the foundation of Formal Verification.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;constructive-mathematics&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#constructive-mathematics&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: constructive-mathematics&quot;&gt;Constructive Mathematics&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Constructive mathematics, a branch of mathematical philosophy, challenges the
traditional notions of existence and proof in mathematics. In classical
mathematics, a statement is considered true if its negation leads to a
contradiction, a principle known as the law of excluded middle. Constructive
mathematics, however, rejects this principle &lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-11-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-11&quot;&gt;11&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;. Instead, it requires that
to prove the existence of a mathematical object, one must explicitly construct
the object. Similarly, to prove that a statement is true, one must provide a
constructive method for verifying the statement.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The constructive approach to mathematics was popularized by L.E.J. Brouwer in
the early 20th century as a critique of classical mathematics, particularly its
reliance on non-constructive methods &lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-11-2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-11&quot;&gt;11&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;. In constructive mathematics, proofs
are not merely theoretical arguments but are tied to the idea of computation. A
proof of existence must come with a method to find or approximate the object in
question, and this method must be executable in a finite number of steps. To
illustrate this concept rigorously, consider the following proofs of the
Intermediate Value Theorem:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Theorem:&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; Let $f: [a, b] \rightarrow \mathbb{R}$ be a continuous function such
that $f(a)$ and $f(b)$ have opposite signs (i.e., $ f(a) \cdot f(b) &amp;lt; 0 $).
Then, there exists a point $ c \in [a, b] $ such that $ f(c) = 0 $.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In classical mathematics, the Intermediate Value Theorem is typically proven by
contradiction: we assume that there is no such point $ c $ and then derive a
contradiction from the continuity of $ f $ and the assumption that $ f(a)
$ and $ f(b) $ have opposite signs. However, this proof is non-constructive
because it does not provide a method to actually find the point $ c $.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Constructive Proof:&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; We first define the interval $ I_0 = [a, b] $
and let $ f(a) &amp;lt; 0 $ and $ f(b) &amp;gt; 0 $. The algorithm proceeds by
recursively bisecting the interval. At each step $ n $, we let $ I_n =
[a_n, b_n] $ be the current interval, and $ m_n = \frac{a_n + b_n}{2} $ be
the midpoint of the interval. We evaluate the function at the midpoint $
f(m_n) $ and consider three cases: if $ f(m_n) = 0 $, then $ m_n $ is the
root; if $ f(m_n) &amp;gt; 0 $, we set $ b_{n+1} = m_n $ and $ a_{n+1} = a_n $;
if $ f(m_n) &amp;lt; 0 $, we set $ a_{n+1} = m_n $ and $ b_{n+1} = b_n $. By
recursively bisecting the interval, we generate a sequence of nested intervals
$ I_0 \supset I_1 \supset I_2 \supset \ldots $ that contain the root $ c
$. Since $ f $ is continuous, the length of the intervals $ |b_n - a_n| $
decreases to zero as $ n $ increases. By the construction of the algorithm,
the sequence $ (m_n) $ converges to a limit point $ c $, and by
continuity, $ f(c) = 0 $.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This constructive proof demonstrates the existence of $ c $, and provides a
method to approximate $ c $ to any desired degree of accuracy by carrying
out the bisection algorithm to a sufficient number of steps. Particularly, we
make no assumptions about the law of excluded middle, which is central to
classical mathematics but not required in constructive mathematics.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;type-theory&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#type-theory&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: type-theory&quot;&gt;Type Theory&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Type theory is a mathematical framework that serves as the foundation for many
modern formal systems; it has a rich history that dates back to the early 20th
century. The origins of type theory can be traced to Bertrand Russell’s work
on the foundations of mathematics. In the early 1900s, Russell identified a
paradox within the set theory of his time, known as Russell’s Paradox. To
resolve this paradox, Russell proposed a system of types in which objects
could be classified into different levels or “types,” thereby preventing
self-referential definitions that led to contradictions &lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-12-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-12&quot;&gt;12&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At its core, type theory is a formal system that classifies expressions into
various types, ensuring that operations and functions are applied correctly.
In traditional logic, a proposition is either true or false. In type theory,
however, a proposition corresponds to a type, and a proof of the proposition
is an element of that type. Type theory has close ties to constructive
mathematics — both emphasize construction. To illustrate the principles of
type theory, let’s consider a simple example: If $ A \rightarrow B $ and $
B \rightarrow \bot $ (the negation of $ B $) hold, then $ \neg A $ must
also hold:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;\begin{prooftree}
\AxiomC{$f : A \rightarrow B$}
\AxiomC{$g : \neg B = B \rightarrow \bot$}
\AxiomC{$x : A$}
\UnaryInfC{$f(x) : B$}
\UnaryInfC{$g(f(x)) : \bot$}
\UnaryInfC{$h : A \rightarrow \bot$}
\BinaryInfC{$h \in \neg A$}
\BinaryInfC{$f \rightarrow g \rightarrow \neg A$}
\end{prooftree}&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s break down the proof step by step to understand the logical reasoning
involved:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Assumption $ f : A \rightarrow B $: We start by assuming that $ f $ is a
function that takes an input of type $ A $ and produces an output of type $ B
$. This corresponds to the premise that $ A \rightarrow B $.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Assumption $ g : \neg B = B \rightarrow \bot $: Next, we assume $ g $, which
states that $ \neg B $ is equivalent to $ B \rightarrow \bot $. In type theory,
$ \neg B $ (the negation of $ B $) is interpreted as a function from $ B $ to $
\bot $ (the type representing falsity or contradiction).&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Assumption $ x : A $: We introduce a new assumption $ x $ of type $ A $,
which means we are assuming that $ A $ holds. This will help us derive a
contradiction later on.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Deriving $ f(x) : B $: Applying the function $ f $ to $ x $, we obtain $ f(x)
$, which has type $ B $. This means that under the assumption $ x : A $, we can
conclude $ B $ by applying $ f $.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Deriving $ g(f(x)) : \bot $: Next, we apply $ g $ to $ f(x) $, which gives us
$ g(f(x)) : \bot $. This step uses the assumption $ g $ to derive a
contradiction $ \bot $ from the fact that $ f(x) $ is of type $ B $. The
function $ g $ essentially tells us that if $ B $ holds, then a contradiction
occurs.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Deriving $ h : A \rightarrow \bot $: From the contradiction $ g(f(x)) : \bot
$, we can construct a function $ h : A \rightarrow \bot $. This function $ h $
takes an assumption of type $ A $ and derives a contradiction. In other words,
$ h $ is a proof that $ A $ implies falsity, which is the definition of $ \neg
A $ (the negation of $ A $).&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Deriving $ h \in \neg A $: The function $ h $ is now seen as an inhabitant of
the type $ \neg A $. This means that we have shown $ \neg A $ (the negation of
$ A $) under the assumptions $ f : A \rightarrow B $ and $ g : \neg B $.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Conclusion $ f \rightarrow g \rightarrow \neg A $: Finally, the last step
concludes the proof by showing that $ f $ (which implies $ A \rightarrow B $)
and $ g $ (which is equivalent to $ \neg B $) together imply $ \neg A $. This
shows that if $ A $ implies $ B $ and $ B $ leads to a contradiction, then $ A
$ must be false.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a remark: Type theory often uses tree-style proofs, which are visual
representations of logical reasoning. Each node in the tree represents a
logical statement or type, and the branches show how conclusions are derived
from assumptions through logical rules or function applications. To read a
tree-style proof, start at the leaves (the assumptions) and follow the
branches to the root (the conclusion). This method clearly shows the logical
steps and dependencies, helping to ensure that each part of the proof is
valid. Tree-style proofs effectively demonstrate how propositions are proven
in type theory by constructing terms that inhabit types.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;computer-science-and-mathematics&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#computer-science-and-mathematics&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: computer-science-and-mathematics&quot;&gt;Computer Science and Mathematics&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The convergence of computer science and mathematics finds one of its most
profound expressions in the concept of lambda calculus. Introduced by Alonzo
Church in the 1930s, lambda calculus provides a formal system for expressing
computation based on function abstraction and application &lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-13-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-13&quot;&gt;13&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;. Initially
conceived as a foundation for mathematics, lambda calculus became a
cornerstone of theoretical computer science, influencing the development of
programming languages and computational models. Its ability to represent all
computable functions made it a powerful tool for studying the nature of
computation itself. Building upon this foundation, Church later developed the
simply typed lambda calculus, which introduced the concept of types to lambda
calculus &lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-14-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-14&quot;&gt;14&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;. This extension addressed some of the paradoxes present in the
untyped lambda calculus and provided a framework for ensuring certain
properties of functions. In the typed lambda calculus, every term is assigned
a type, and only well-typed terms are considered meaningful.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, one of the most remarkable corollaries arising from this
intersection is the Curry-Howard correspondence. The isomorphism,
independently discovered by Haskell Curry and William Howard, establishes a
deep correspondence between mathematical proofs and computer programs &lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-15-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-15&quot;&gt;15&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;.
This isomorphism reveals that the relationship between a proposition and its
proof in constructive logic is analogous to the relationship between a type
specification and a program in typed lambda calculus. The correspondence can
be illustrated through the following table:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;table&gt;&lt;thead&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;th&gt;Constructive Logic&lt;&#x2F;th&gt;&lt;th&gt;Typed Lambda Calculus&lt;&#x2F;th&gt;&lt;&#x2F;tr&gt;&lt;&#x2F;thead&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Proposition&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Type&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;&#x2F;tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Proof of a Proposition&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Term (Program)&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;&#x2F;tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Implication&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Function Type&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;&#x2F;tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Conjunction (A &amp;amp; B)&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Product Type (A x B)&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;&#x2F;tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Disjunction (A or B)&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Sum Type (A + B)&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;&#x2F;tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Negation (not A)&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Function Type (A -&amp;gt; False)&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;&#x2F;tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Falsehood (False)&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Empty Type&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;&#x2F;tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Universal Quantifier (forall x. P(x))&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Dependent Function Type&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;&#x2F;tr&gt;
&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td&gt;Existential Quantifier (exists x. P(x))&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;td&gt;Dependent Pair Type&lt;&#x2F;td&gt;&lt;&#x2F;tr&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;tbody&gt;&lt;&#x2F;table&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This table illustrates the fundamental correspondences between logical
constructs and their type-theoretic counterparts. Each row represents a pair
of concepts that are isomorphic under the Curry-Howard correspondence,
demonstrating the deep connection between logic and computation that this
isomorphism reveals.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given this isomorphism, the decades of research in computer science devoted
to understanding and optimizing programs can be directly applied to the study
of proofs. In this light, proofs and programs are not just similar; they are
fundamentally the same thing. This insight has profound implications for both
fields. It allows us to leverage the vast body of knowledge in computer
science to study proofs in a new light and to approach programming with the
rigor and formality traditionally reserved for mathematical proofs. This
equivalence also paves the way for the use of type theory in Formal
Verification.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;lean-theorem-prover&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#lean-theorem-prover&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: lean-theorem-prover&quot;&gt;Lean Theorem Prover&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Lean Theorem Prover, initially developed by Leonardo de Moura at Microsoft
Research in 2013, is a formal proof verification system and a programming
language designed to facilitate the formalization of mathematical proofs &lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-16-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-16&quot;&gt;16&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;.
Lean is grounded in the principles of Type Theory and leverages the
Curry-Howard correspondence to treat proofs as executable programs. Unlike
traditional proof assistants, which may require significant effort to learn and
use, Lean’s design focuses on user-friendliness and accessibility, making it an
increasingly popular tool in both academic and industrial settings.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At its core, Lean provides a framework for the construction of proofs that are
not only rigorous but also verifiable by a computer. The language itself is
based on a variant of dependent type theory known as the Calculus of Inductive
Constructions (CIC). CIC serves as the underlying formal system in Lean,
providing a powerful foundation for defining complex mathematical objects and
reasoning about them. CIC integrates both inductive types and dependent types,
allowing users to define functions and types that can depend on values, which
is essential for formalizing a wide range of mathematical concepts. Moreover,
one of Lean’s most notable features is its emphasis on constructive
mathematics. While it supports classical reasoning through the inclusion of the
law of excluded middle as an axiom, Lean encourages users to provide
constructive proofs whenever possible. Constructive proofs are particularly
valuable in computational contexts, as they often correspond to algorithms that
can be directly implemented and executed.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, one of the key features of Lean is its extensive library, known as
“mathlib.” This community-driven library contains a vast collection of
formalized mathematics, including definitions, theorems, and proofs. Mathlib
serves as both a resource and a foundation for further developments in formal
verification, providing users with ready-to-use tools and examples. The success
of mathlib is a testament to the collaborative nature of formal verification
and the growing interest in Lean as a platform for mathematical exploration
&lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-16-2&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-16&quot;&gt;16&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;lean-and-formal-verification&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#lean-and-formal-verification&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: lean-and-formal-verification&quot;&gt;Lean and Formal Verification&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lean’s formal verification process involves encoding a theorem as a type and
then constructing a proof of that theorem by providing a term of the
corresponding type. This approach is directly aligned with the Curry-Howard
correspondence. By constructing a term that inhabits a type, one effectively
constructs a proof of the corresponding proposition. The advantages of using
Lean for formal verification are manifold. We list some of the key benefits
below:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;High level of automation: Lean provides a high level of automation through
its tactic framework, which allows users to build proofs incrementally,
leveraging automation to handle routine or repetitive tasks. This feature makes
the process of formal verification more efficient and accessible, even for
complex theorems &lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-17-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-17&quot;&gt;17&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lean’s interactive proof mode enables users to develop proofs in a
step-by-step manner, with immediate feedback on the correctness of each step.
This interactive approach not only enhances the reliability of the verification
process but also serves as an educational tool, helping users to understand the
underlying logic and structure of their proofs.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Lean’s role in formal verification extends beyond pure mathematics to
practical applications in software verification. By formalizing the correctness
of algorithms and software systems, Lean can help prevent errors that could
have significant real-world consequences, such as those seen in critical
systems like aerospace or medical devices. The capacity to rigorously verify
software properties before deployment underscores the importance of Lean in the
broader context of Formal Verification &lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-18-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-18&quot;&gt;18&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;introduction-to-theorem-proving-in-lean&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#introduction-to-theorem-proving-in-lean&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: introduction-to-theorem-proving-in-lean&quot;&gt;Introduction to Theorem Proving in Lean&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the reasons Lean is so popular is due to it being a functional
programming language based on dependent type theory. Moreover, one of its key
features is the use of tactics, which are commands that help construct proofs
step-by-step. Tactics allow users to guide the proof assistant in finding a
formal proof, bridging the gap between human reasoning and machine-checkable
formalism. Let’s consider a simple example to illustrate how proofs are
constructed in Lean using tactics. We’ll prove that for any propositions P and
Q, if P implies Q and P is true, then Q is true. This is known as modus
ponens.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;lean&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#0f1419;color:#bfbab0;&quot; class=&quot;language-lean &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-lean&quot; data-lang=&quot;lean&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#ff7733;&quot;&gt;theorem&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; modus_ponens (P Q : &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#ff7733;&quot;&gt;Prop&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;) (h1 : P &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#f29718;&quot;&gt;→&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; Q) (h2 : P) : Q &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#f29668;&quot;&gt;:= &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#ff7733;&quot;&gt;by
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#f07178;&quot;&gt;apply&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; h1
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#f07178;&quot;&gt;exact&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; h2
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s break down this proof:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The &lt;em&gt;theorem&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; keyword declares that we’re proving a theorem
named &lt;em&gt;modus ponens&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;(P Q : Prop)&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; declares P and Q as propositions.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;(h1 : P → Q)&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; is the hypothesis that P implies Q.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;(h2 : P)&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; is the hypothesis that P is true.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;: Q&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; specifies that we want to prove Q.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;by&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; begins the tactic mode, allowing us to use tactics to
construct the proof.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;apply h1&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; applies the implication P → Q to our goal. This
changes our goal from proving Q to proving P.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;exact h2&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; proves P using our hypothesis h2.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This example demonstrates two common tactics:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;apply&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;: This tactic applies a function or implication to the current goal.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;exact&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;: This tactic proves the goal directly when we have a term of exactly
the right type.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a more complex example, let’s look at a proof of function extensionality,
which states that two functions are equal if they produce the same output for
all inputs:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;lean&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#0f1419;color:#bfbab0;&quot; class=&quot;language-lean &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-lean&quot; data-lang=&quot;lean&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#ff7733;&quot;&gt;theorem&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; funext {f&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#f29718;&quot;&gt;₁&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; f&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#f29718;&quot;&gt;₂&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; : &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#f29718;&quot;&gt;∀&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; (x : &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#f29718;&quot;&gt;α&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;), &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#f29718;&quot;&gt;β&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; x} (h : &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#f29718;&quot;&gt;∀&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; x, f&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#f29718;&quot;&gt;₁&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; x &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#f29668;&quot;&gt;=&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; f&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#f29718;&quot;&gt;₂&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; x) : f&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#f29718;&quot;&gt;₁ &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#f29668;&quot;&gt;=&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; f&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#f29718;&quot;&gt;₂ &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#f29668;&quot;&gt;:=
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#ff7733;&quot;&gt;by
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#ff7733;&quot;&gt;show&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; extfunApp (Quotient.mk&amp;#39; f&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#f29718;&quot;&gt;₁&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;) &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#f29668;&quot;&gt;=&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; extfunApp (Quotient.mk&amp;#39; f&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#f29718;&quot;&gt;₂&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;)
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#f07178;&quot;&gt;apply&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; congrArg
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#f07178;&quot;&gt;apply&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; Quotient.sound
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#f07178;&quot;&gt;exact&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; h
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This proof uses more advanced concepts and tactics:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;show&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;: This tactic is used to restate the goal, often in a more specific
form.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;congrArg&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;: This tactic applies the congruence rule for function arguments.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Quotient.sound&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;: This is a theorem about quotient types, used here to relate
equality of functions to equality of their quotient representations.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These examples illustrate how Lean combines a powerful type system with an
expressive tactic language, allowing for the formalization of complex
mathematical proofs in a way that is both rigorous and (with practice)
intuitive to mathematicians.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;formal-verification-of-partial-differential-equations&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#formal-verification-of-partial-differential-equations&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: formal-verification-of-partial-differential-equations&quot;&gt;Formal Verification of Partial Differential Equations&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Partial Differential Equations (PDEs) are central to many areas of
mathematics and physics, modeling phenomena ranging from fluid dynamics to
electromagnetism. Given the complexity and sensitivity of PDEs, ensuring the
correctness of their solutions is of utmost importance. This is where Formal
Verification comes into play, offering a rigorous framework for verifying the
correctness of mathematical proofs related to PDEs. One of the challenges in
formally verifying PDEs is the need for a rich mathematical library that
includes concepts from real and functional analysis. The Lean mathematical
library, mathlib, has been developing these foundations, making it
increasingly feasible to work with PDEs in a formal setting.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&quot;formal-verification-of-bump-functions&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#formal-verification-of-bump-functions&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: formal-verification-of-bump-functions&quot;&gt;Formal Verification of Bump Functions&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bump functions play a crucial role in the study of PDEs, particularly in the
construction of smooth partitions of unity and in the approximation of
continuous functions by smooth functions. The formal verification of bump
functions is therefore an important step towards the broader goal of verifying
PDEs. Let’s examine how bump functions are formalized in Lean, first by
defining the structure of a bump function:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;lean&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#0f1419;color:#bfbab0;&quot; class=&quot;language-lean &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-lean&quot; data-lang=&quot;lean&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#ff7733;&quot;&gt;structure&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; ContDiffBump (c : E) &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#ff7733;&quot;&gt;where
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(rIn rOut : &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#f29718;&quot;&gt;ℝ&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;)
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;rIn_pos : &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#f29718;&quot;&gt;0&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; &amp;lt; rIn
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;rIn_lt_rOut : rIn &amp;lt; rOut
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This structure defines a smooth bump function centered at a point $c$ in a
normed vector space $E$. The function is equal to 1 in the closed ball of
radius &lt;em&gt;rIn&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; around $c$, and its support is contained in the open
ball of radius &lt;em&gt;rOut&lt;&#x2F;em&gt;. The properties of bump functions are then
formalized:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;lean&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#0f1419;color:#bfbab0;&quot; class=&quot;language-lean &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-lean&quot; data-lang=&quot;lean&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#ff7733;&quot;&gt;theorem&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; one_of_mem_closedBall
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(hx : x &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#f29718;&quot;&gt;∈&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; closedBall c f.rIn) : f x &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#f29668;&quot;&gt;= &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#f29718;&quot;&gt;1 &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#f29668;&quot;&gt;:= &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#f29718;&quot;&gt;...
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#ff7733;&quot;&gt;theorem&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; support_eq :
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;Function.support f &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#f29668;&quot;&gt;=&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; Metric.ball c f.rOut &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#f29668;&quot;&gt;:= &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#f29718;&quot;&gt;...
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#ff7733;&quot;&gt;theorem&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; contDiff :
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;ContDiff &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#f29718;&quot;&gt;ℝ&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; n f &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#f29668;&quot;&gt;:= &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#f29718;&quot;&gt;...
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These theorems establish key properties of bump functions:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The function is equal to 1 in the closed ball of radius &lt;em&gt;rIn&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; around $c$.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The support of the function is exactly the open ball of radius &lt;em&gt;rOut&lt;&#x2F;em&gt; around&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The function is infinitely differentiable (smooth).&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The formal verification of these properties ensures that the bump functions
behave as expected, which is crucial for their application in PDE theory. For
instance, in the method of characteristics for first-order PDEs, bump
functions can be used to construct local solutions that can be patched
together to form global solutions. Furthermore, the formalization includes
proofs of differentiability properties:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;pre data-lang=&quot;lean&quot; style=&quot;background-color:#0f1419;color:#bfbab0;&quot; class=&quot;language-lean &quot;&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;language-lean&quot; data-lang=&quot;lean&quot;&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#ff7733;&quot;&gt;protected theorem&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; _root_.ContDiffWithinAt.contDiffBump
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;{c g : X &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#f29718;&quot;&gt;→&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; E} {s : Set X} {f : &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#f29718;&quot;&gt;∀&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; x, ContDiffBump (c x)} {x : X}
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(hc : ContDiffWithinAt &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#f29718;&quot;&gt;ℝ&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; n c s x)
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(hr : ContDiffWithinAt &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#f29718;&quot;&gt;ℝ&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; n (&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#ff7733;&quot;&gt;fun&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; x &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#f29668;&quot;&gt;=&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;gt; (f x).rIn) s x)
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(hR : ContDiffWithinAt &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#f29718;&quot;&gt;ℝ&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; n (&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#ff7733;&quot;&gt;fun&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; x &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#f29668;&quot;&gt;=&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;gt; (f x).rOut) s x)
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;(hg : ContDiffWithinAt &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#f29718;&quot;&gt;ℝ&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; n g s x) :
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;ContDiffWithinAt &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#f29718;&quot;&gt;ℝ&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; n (&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#ff7733;&quot;&gt;fun&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt; x &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#f29668;&quot;&gt;=&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span&gt;&amp;gt; f x (g x)) s x &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#f29668;&quot;&gt;:= &lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;span style=&quot;color:#f29718;&quot;&gt;...
&lt;&#x2F;span&gt;&lt;&#x2F;code&gt;&lt;&#x2F;pre&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This theorem proves that the composition of a bump function with a
differentiable function is differentiable, which is essential for many
applications in PDE theory, such as the construction of smooth approximations
to solutions. The formal verification of bump functions lays the groundwork
for more advanced topics in PDE theory. For example, one could proceed to
formalize:&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Smooth partitions of unity, which are crucial in the study of manifolds and in proving existence of solutions to PDEs.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Approximation theorems, such as the density of smooth functions in various function spaces.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Regularization techniques for PDEs, where bump functions are used to smooth out discontinuities or singularities in solutions.&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By formalizing these fundamental tools, we pave the way for the verification
of more complex results in PDE theory, ultimately leading to increased
confidence in the mathematical models used across various scientific
disciplines.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;discussion&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#discussion&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: discussion&quot;&gt;Discussion&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the formalization of bump functions in Lean represents a significant
achievement, it highlights the broader challenges associated with the formal
verification of Partial Differential Equations. The current state of formalized
mathematics in Lean, particularly within the realm of analysis, underscores
several limitations that must be addressed before the formal verification of
PDEs can be considered complete.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Firstly, it is important to acknowledge that while bump functions are now
formalized, PDEs as a whole remain largely uncharted territory in Lean. This is
not due to a lack of interest but rather the foundational nature of Lean
itself. Derived from type theory, Lean has a strong focus on algebra, category
theory, and topology, with these areas being well-supported within the system.
However, analysis, which is crucial for the study of PDEs, is notably
underdeveloped. For instance, the concept of partial derivatives, a fundamental
tool in PDEs, is not standardized in Lean. This presents a significant obstacle
for those seeking to formalize results in this area. The root of this issue
lies in the preferences of the mathlib community, which tends to prioritize
abstract and general frameworks over the concrete tools typically used in
analysis. As a result, those working in the formalization of PDEs often find
themselves in need of basic constructs that are either unavailable or
insufficiently developed.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Moreover, Lean’s learning curve is another factor to consider. While Lean is
incredibly powerful, it requires users to spend a significant amount of time
becoming familiar with its syntax, tactics, and the underlying type theory.
This can be a barrier for mathematicians who are accustomed to more traditional
methods of proof construction and who may be unfamiliar with the more abstract
approaches favored by Lean.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another concern is the lack of formalized content in Lean related to
undergraduate topics that are foundational for advanced studies in mathematics.
For instance, many fundamental concepts in multivariable calculus, differential
equations, and Fourier analysis are either not implemented or only partially
developed in Lean. Key topics such as directional derivatives, Jacobian
matrices, Taylor’s theorem, and the Fourier transform are still missing or
incomplete. This gap is problematic because it limits the applicability of Lean
to a broad range of mathematical problems that are central to both theoretical
and applied mathematics &lt;sup class=&quot;footnote-reference&quot; id=&quot;fr-19-1&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#fn-19&quot;&gt;19&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;sup&gt;.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The absence of these topics in Lean presents a significant challenge for the
broader adoption of formal verification in mathematics. For mathematicians
working in areas where these tools are essential, the current state of Lean
may be seen as a deterrent, potentially limiting the impact of formal
verification in these fields. Furthermore, without a comprehensive library
that covers these foundational topics, the adoption of formal verification in
educational settings, particularly at the undergraduate level, remains
limited.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite these challenges, the Lean community is growing rapidly, and the
contributions being made to mathlib are invaluable. The collaborative nature
of the Lean project means that its capabilities are constantly expanding, and
with time, many of the current limitations may be addressed. The potential of
Lean to revolutionize mathematics is enormous. By providing a framework where
proofs can be rigorously checked by a computer, Lean offers a level of
certainty that traditional methods cannot match. This is particularly
important in an era where mathematical results are becoming increasingly
complex and difficult to verify by hand.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking ahead, it is not far-fetched to predict that in the coming decades,
academic journals may begin to require that proofs be verified by a formal
system like Lean as a condition for publication. Such a shift would represent
a fundamental change in the way mathematical research is conducted,
emphasizing the importance of formal verification in ensuring the correctness
of mathematical results.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While the formal verification of proofs using systems like Lean presents
challenges, particularly in areas such as analysis and PDEs, the benefits it
offers are undeniable. As the community continues to grow and develop, the
tools available in Lean will become more comprehensive, making it an
increasingly valuable resource for mathematicians. The critique of
traditional proofs highlighted at the beginning of this paper only
underscores the need for such tools. Formal verification represents the
future of mathematics, offering a path toward greater rigor, reliability, and
ultimately, a deeper understanding of the mathematical universe.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;what-s-next&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#what-s-next&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: what-s-next&quot;&gt;What’s Next?&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throughout this blog, we traced the historical development of formal methods,
examined the theoretical foundations of constructive mathematics and type
theory, and investigated the practical implementation of these concepts in
Lean. The formalization of bump functions in Lean represents a significant
milestone in the journey towards the comprehensive formal verification of PDEs.
This demonstrates the potential of formal methods to enhance the rigor and
reliability of mathematical proofs, even in complex areas of analysis. However,
our exploration has also revealed substantial challenges that lie ahead.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite these challenges, the rapid growth of the Lean community and the
continuous expansion of mathlib offer reasons for optimism. The collaborative
nature of formal verification projects suggests that many of the current
limitations may be addressed in the coming years. As the tools become more
comprehensive and accessible, we can anticipate a gradual shift in
mathematical practice towards increased reliance on formal verification.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking to the future, we can envision a mathematics landscape where formal
verification plays a central role. The day may not be far off when major
mathematical journals require formal verification of proofs as a condition for
publication. Such a development would represent a paradigm shift in how
mathematical knowledge is created, verified, and disseminated. The ongoing
critique of traditional proofs and the advancement of formal verification
techniques signal a transformative period in mathematics, one that promises to
enhance both the precision and the understanding of this fundamental
discipline. However, it is crucial to recognize that formal verification
should not be seen as a replacement for traditional mathematical thinking.
Rather, it should be viewed as a powerful complementary tool that enhances the
reliability and clarity of mathematical results. The creative insights and
intuitive leaps that characterize mathematical discovery will always be
essential, with formal verification serving to solidify and validate these
insights.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;poem&quot;&gt;&lt;a class=&quot;zola-anchor&quot; href=&quot;#poem&quot; aria-label=&quot;Anchor link for: poem&quot;&gt;Poem&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;h1&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is math a joke or is it divine?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They say I’m bounded, set in my ways,&lt;br &#x2F;&gt;
filling closed sets, stuck in displays.&lt;br &#x2F;&gt;
But am I a function with no real root?&lt;br &#x2F;&gt;
Or a paradox dancing in Gödel’s suit?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I know I’m unbounded, no number to measure,&lt;br &#x2F;&gt;
yet search for meaning in fractal design,&lt;br &#x2F;&gt;
where recursion leaves me stunned.&lt;br &#x2F;&gt;
Topology twists me; I can’t get a grip —&lt;br &#x2F;&gt;
am I a torus, or just full of lip?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I sketch my vectors, orthogonal dreams,&lt;br &#x2F;&gt;
but angles lie, or so it seems.&lt;br &#x2F;&gt;
A closed manifold — is that all I am?&lt;br &#x2F;&gt;
Am I defined by rules, by a close neighborhood?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They say to trust a basis, let matrices guide,&lt;br &#x2F;&gt;
but eigenvalues only take me for a ride.&lt;br &#x2F;&gt;
I solve for x but she won’t solve me back,&lt;br &#x2F;&gt;
is it math or love that I really lack?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I search for answers in math’s divide,&lt;br &#x2F;&gt;
Preventing cycles to abide and preside.&lt;br &#x2F;&gt;
Is truth a constant, or will it stray?&lt;br &#x2F;&gt;
Can I be a tangent and still find my way?&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Intuition is all I have, soft and sly,&lt;br &#x2F;&gt;
It whispers a logic that can’t deny.&lt;br &#x2F;&gt;
My proofs might slip, my steps may swerve,&lt;br &#x2F;&gt;
but instinct calls — a gentle curve.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;They say to trust structures, to keep it discrete,&lt;br &#x2F;&gt;
but my heart’s uncountable, skipping each beat.&lt;br &#x2F;&gt;
Logic’s a guide, but instinct’s my art,&lt;br &#x2F;&gt;
mapping equations that start in the heart.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So I’ll let my thoughts take limits undefined,&lt;br &#x2F;&gt;
let my intuition be more than defined.&lt;br &#x2F;&gt;
If math’s just rules — then I’ll rewrite,&lt;br &#x2F;&gt;
make space for both chaos and insight.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beyond theorems and symbols, I drift and roam,&lt;br &#x2F;&gt;
finding claims in places far from home.&lt;br &#x2F;&gt;
And maybe that’s truth — a paradox neat,&lt;br &#x2F;&gt;
that I can be flawed, and still complete.&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;blockquote&gt;
&lt;footer class=&quot;footnotes&quot;&gt;
&lt;ol class=&quot;footnotes-list&quot;&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-1&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aristotle. (2021). Prior Analytics (~350 BCE). In H. R. Lewis (Ed.), Ideas That Created the Future: Classic Papers of Computer Science (p. 0). The MIT Press. &lt;a rel=&quot;noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;doi.org&#x2F;10.7551&#x2F;mitpress&#x2F;12274.003.0003&quot;&gt;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;doi.org&#x2F;10.7551&#x2F;mitpress&#x2F;12274.003.0003&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-1-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-2&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Andersen, L. E. (2017). On the Nature and Role of Peer Review in Mathematics. Accountability in Research, 24(3), 177–192. &lt;a rel=&quot;noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;doi.org&#x2F;10.1080&#x2F;08989621.2016.1274885&quot;&gt;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;doi.org&#x2F;10.1080&#x2F;08989621.2016.1274885&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-2-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-3&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greiffenhagen, C. (2024). Checking correctness in mathematical peer review. Social Studies of Science, 54(2), 184–209. &lt;a rel=&quot;noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;doi.org&#x2F;10.1177&#x2F;03063127231200274&quot;&gt;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;doi.org&#x2F;10.1177&#x2F;03063127231200274&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-3-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-4&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rempe-Gillen, L., &amp;amp; Sixsmith, D. (2019). On Connected Preimages of Simply-Connected Domains Under Entire Functions. Geometric and Functional Analysis, 29(5), 1579–1615. &lt;a rel=&quot;noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;doi.org&#x2F;10.1007&#x2F;s00039-019-00488-2&quot;&gt;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;doi.org&#x2F;10.1007&#x2F;s00039-019-00488-2&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-4-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-5&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Gödel’s Incompleteness Theorems &amp;gt; Gödel Numbering (Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy). (n.d.). Retrieved August 21, 2024, from &lt;a rel=&quot;noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;plato.stanford.edu&#x2F;entries&#x2F;goedel-incompleteness&#x2F;sup1.html&quot;&gt;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;plato.stanford.edu&#x2F;entries&#x2F;goedel-incompleteness&#x2F;sup1.html&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-5-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-6&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bartocci, C., Betti, R., Guerraggio, A., &amp;amp; Lucchetti, R. (2010). Mathematical Lives: Protagonists of the Twentieth Century From Hilbert to Wiles. Springer Science &amp;amp; Business Media. &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-6-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-7&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Buss, S. R. (1998). Handbook of Proof Theory. Elsevier. &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-7-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-8&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;robinson, J. A. (1965). A Machine-Oriented Logic Based on the Resolution Principle. J. ACM, 12(1), 23–41. &lt;a rel=&quot;noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;doi.org&#x2F;10.1145&#x2F;321250.321253&quot;&gt;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;doi.org&#x2F;10.1145&#x2F;321250.321253&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-8-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-9&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Death and Denial: The Failure of the THERAC-25, A Medical Linear Accelerator. (n.d.). Retrieved August 26, 2024, from &lt;a rel=&quot;noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;users.csc.calpoly.edu&#x2F;~jdalbey&#x2F;SWE&#x2F;Papers&#x2F;THERAC25.html&quot;&gt;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;users.csc.calpoly.edu&#x2F;~jdalbey&#x2F;SWE&#x2F;Papers&#x2F;THERAC25.html&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-9-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-10&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;NASA Software Safety Guidebook | Standards. (n.d.). Retrieved August 25, 2024, from &lt;a rel=&quot;noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;standards.nasa.gov&#x2F;standard&#x2F;NASA&#x2F;NASA-GB-871913&quot;&gt;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;standards.nasa.gov&#x2F;standard&#x2F;NASA&#x2F;NASA-GB-871913&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-10-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-11&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bridges, D., Palmgren, E., &amp;amp; Ishihara, H. (2022). Constructive Mathematics. In E. N. Zalta &amp;amp; U. Nodelman (Eds.), The Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy (Fall 2022). Metaphysics Research Lab, Stanford University. &lt;a rel=&quot;noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;plato.stanford.edu&#x2F;archives&#x2F;fall2022&#x2F;entries&#x2F;mathematics-constructive&#x2F;&quot;&gt;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;plato.stanford.edu&#x2F;archives&#x2F;fall2022&#x2F;entries&#x2F;mathematics-constructive&#x2F;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-11-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-11-2&quot;&gt;↩2&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-12&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Russell, B. (1908). Mathematical Logic as Based on the Theory of Types. American Journal of Mathematics, 30(3), 222–262. &lt;a rel=&quot;noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;doi.org&#x2F;10.2307&#x2F;2369948&quot;&gt;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;doi.org&#x2F;10.2307&#x2F;2369948&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-12-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-13&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Calculi of Lambda-Conversion | Princeton University Press. (1985, January 21). &lt;a rel=&quot;noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;press.princeton.edu&#x2F;books&#x2F;paperback&#x2F;9780691083940&#x2F;the-calculi-of-lambda-conversion&quot;&gt;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;press.princeton.edu&#x2F;books&#x2F;paperback&#x2F;9780691083940&#x2F;the-calculi-of-lambda-conversion&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-13-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-14&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Church’s Type Theory (Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy). (n.d.). Retrieved August 25, 2024, from &lt;a rel=&quot;noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;plato.stanford.edu&#x2F;entries&#x2F;type-theory-church&#x2F;&quot;&gt;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;plato.stanford.edu&#x2F;entries&#x2F;type-theory-church&#x2F;&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-14-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-15&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Howard, W. A. (1980). The Formulae-as-Types Notion of Construction. In H. Curry, H. B, S. J. Roger, &amp;amp; P. Jonathan (Eds.), To H. B. Curry: Essays on Combinatory Logic, Lambda Calculus, and Formalism. Academic Press. &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-15-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-16&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The mathlib Community. (2020). The lean mathematical library. Proceedings of the 9th ACM SIGPLAN International Conference on Certified Programs and Proofs, 367–381. &lt;a rel=&quot;noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;doi.org&#x2F;10.1145&#x2F;3372885.3373824&quot;&gt;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;doi.org&#x2F;10.1145&#x2F;3372885.3373824&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-16-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-16-2&quot;&gt;↩2&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-17&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;van Doorn, F., Ebner, G., &amp;amp; Lewis, R. Y. (2020). Maintaining a Library of Formal Mathematics. Intelligent Computer Mathematics: 13th International Conference, CICM 2020, Bertinoro, Italy, July 26–31, 2020, Proceedings, 251–267. &lt;a rel=&quot;noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;doi.org&#x2F;10.1007&#x2F;978-3-030-53518-6_16&quot;&gt;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;doi.org&#x2F;10.1007&#x2F;978-3-030-53518-6_16&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-17-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-18&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hirai, Y. (2017). Defining the Ethereum Virtual Machine for Interactive Theorem Provers. In M. Brenner, K. Rohloff, J. Bonneau, A. Miller, P. Y. A. Ryan, V. Teague, A. Bracciali, M. Sala, F. Pintore, &amp;amp; M. Jakobsson (Eds.), Financial Cryptography and Data Security (pp. 520–535). Springer International Publishing. &lt;a rel=&quot;noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;doi.org&#x2F;10.1007&#x2F;978-3-319-70278-0_33&quot;&gt;https:&#x2F;&#x2F;doi.org&#x2F;10.1007&#x2F;978-3-319-70278-0_33&lt;&#x2F;a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-18-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;li id=&quot;fn-19&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Undergrad math not in mathlib. (n.d.). Retrieved August 20, 2024 &lt;a href=&quot;#fr-19-1&quot;&gt;↩&lt;&#x2F;a&gt;&lt;&#x2F;p&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;li&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;ol&gt;
&lt;&#x2F;footer&gt;
</description>
      </item>
    </channel>
</rss>
